本字幕由✿花語&花丸字幕組✿共同製作
面が
The mask...
青龍様の面が
The Blue Dragon's mask...
どうしたの
What's wrong?
あの目を見ると 石になるんだ
Looking at his eyes will turn you to stone!
石？
Stone?
H-He's come to kill us.
俺達を殺しに来たんだ
青龍は私を助けてくれた
The Blue Dragon saved me.
理由もなく人を殺したりなんか
He wouldn't kill without reason.
目を閉じた
He closed his eyes.
敵意がないと 知らせるため？
Is he telling them he means no harm?
Episode 14:      Light
何をしに来た 青龍
Why did you come here, Blue Dragon?
其方 我々とともに行く気がないのだろう
You have no intention of coming with us, do you?
If you've come to help us escape, say so!
其方 脱出の手助けに来たなら 口で言わぬか
四龍同士で戦わねばならぬのかと絶望したぞ
I despaired at the thought that I might have to fight another dragon warrior!
Where are you digging, anyway?
と言うか そなた どこを掘っている
The exit is over there.
出口はあちらだぞ
ここ 外に繋がってる
This leads to the outside.
ここを崩す方が早い
It's faster to break through here.
それを早く言わぬか
You should have said that sooner!
姫様 すぐに掘りますのでお待ちを
Princess, I will dig us out of here momentarily.
私も掘るわ
I'll help dig too.
ちょっと貸して
Let me see that.
Huh? Um...
え あの
行けません 姫様をお助けするのは 我ら四龍の役目
You mustn't. Rescuing the princess is our responsibility as dragon warriors!
Our?
私にも
Let me...
Our?
私にもやらせて
Let me help!
一刻も早くここを出よう
Let's get out of here as soon as possible!
はい
Yes, Princess!
あんた達も命が惜しいかったら 堀りな
If you guys want to live, help us dig.
What? With my bare hands...
I have two. Use one
ハク
Hak...
ハクは無事
Are you all right, Hak?
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
I'll come back.
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
私 帰るから
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
S
a
h
l
s
絶対に帰るから
I promise I'll come back!
クソ 固いな
Damn. It's solid.
どれだけ埋まってるんだ
Just how much is there?
いや
No...
絶対助けす
I will rescue her!
何だ
What?
む 息子がその先に埋まってて
M-My son is trapped in there.
俺の仲間は青龍を探しに行って埋まった
My friends got trapped
while looking for the Blue Dragon.
あんたらの家族もその辺りに居ると
You say your family members
are in there as well?
答えろ
Answer me.
今隠しても得はないぞ
Hiding the truth now won't help you.
長老 外からなら...
Elder, if we dig from the outside...
しかし
But...
What is it?
なんだ
知ってる事があったら言え
If you know something, tell me.
仲間の命が係ってるんだ
My friends' lives are at stake.
早くしろ
Hurry up.
悪いな なりふり構っていられないんでね
Sorry, but I don't have
any time to waste.
諦めない
I won't give up.
もっと壊して 早くここを出るんだ
I have to break more rocks and get out of here.
Blue Dragon...
青龍...
大丈夫
Are you all right?
青龍 そなたの部屋に姫様をお連れてしろ
Blue Dragon, take the princess to your room.
ここよりは息苦しくないはず
It should be easier to breathe there.
平気
I'm fine.
平気だってば
I said I'm fine.
I-I'm not cold. I'm fine.
さ 寒くないよ 平気よ
優しい人
He's a kind person.
どうして
Why...
Why doesn't anyone try to understand the Blue Dragon's kindness?
どうして青龍の優しさを誰も分かろうとしないんだろう
ここに来たのだって きっと里の人を心配したからなのに
He probably came here because
he was worried about the villagers.
きっとそうやって ずっと彼なりに里の人を守ってきたのに
I'm sure he's protected the villagers
in his own way all this time.
くやしい
It's frustrating.
貴方が一人でいるのが悔しいわ
I hate to see you alone like this.
会ったばかりの貴方の力になりたいなんて
Is it presumptuous of me to want to help you...
when we've only just met?
私の思い上がりかな
Okay.
よし
I can keep going.
まだやれる
I can keep trying.
私は頑張れる
私ね青龍 十五年間ずっと外に出た事なかったの
Blue Dragon, for fifteen years, I didn't go outside.
何の不安もない日々
My life was free of concerns.
Within my tiny world, I protected my tiny happiness.
私は小さいな世界で小さいな幸せを守ってた
それが突然奪われて分かったの
When it was suddenly taken from me, I learned...
ひもじい思いをする事
what it means to be hungry.
心を潰される思いがある事
How it feels to have your heart broken.
The knowledge that, nonetheless,
you must keep breathing...
それでも呼吸を止めない事
that you still desire to live.
生きたいと願う事
I am alive.
私が生きる事 貴方が生きる事 無意味だ何て言わせない
So are you.
I won't let anyone say it's pointless.
So I'll tear down this darkness for you.
だからこんな暗闇 打ち破ってあげる
青龍が青龍のまま手足を伸ばせる場所に必ず連れていくからね
I'll take you to a place where you can stretch your legs and be yourself!
そんな場所 あるのだろうか
Does such a place exist?
Where can I find it?
どこに行けばあるのだろう
いや 本当はもう 分かっているんじゃないのか
No. Don't I know already?
ま まだか外
H-How much further to the outside?
姫様 お休みになって下さい
Princess, you should rest.
I'm fine.
私は大丈夫
大丈夫
Are you okay?
I'm fine.
平気
Princess!
姫さん
Hak!
ハク
Hak...
本当はもう分かっていたんだ
In truth, I already knew...
from the moment I first saw her.
彼女を初めて見た時から
あの少女の傍らに光ある場所があると
There is a place full of light at this girl's side.
ハク よくあの場所が分かったわね
Hak, I'm surprised you knew where to dig.
里の連中に聞き出した
I got it out of the villagers.
家族の命が係って初めて連中は秘密を吐露した
When their families' lives were endangered, they finally confessed their secret.
I'm glad they wouldn't abandon their families.
よかった 家族をも見捨てる人達じゃなくて
Inability to overcome fear is human.
恐怖に勝てないのも人ゆえ...だよ
それで あれをどうするんだ 姫さん
What are you going to do
about that, Princess?
それが困ったわ
It's a problem.
I can't give up on him.
諦めきれないの
青龍
Blue Dragon!
もう一度言うわ
I'll say it again.
一緒に行こう
Let's travel together.
I want to take you with me.
貴方を連れて行きたい
I...
俺は
私の前では目を閉じなくていいの
You don't have to close your eyes with me.
Does your power truly allow you
to kill indiscriminately?
あなたの力は本当に無差別に人を殺めるもの
アオがこんなに貴方に懐いてるのに
Even though Ao loves you so much?
Ao knows.
アオは分かってるのよ
貴方は破滅なんかじゃない
You are not destructive.
許されるのなら この姿のまま生きてもいい
Can I be allowed to live, given the way I am?
「構わない」と言うその手を握り返してもいいだろうか
Can I grasp the hand of someone
who says she doesn't mind?
Can I trust her?
信じてもいいだろうか
さてと 行きますか
Let's go, okay?
お世話になりました
Thank you for your hospitality!
ごめん...な
I'm sorry...
for leaving you alone.
お前 一人にして ごめんな
I'm sorry!
I'm fine now.
もう 平気だよ
鈴の音がなくても
Would you laugh
if I told you I made friends I can talk to
without the sound of bells?
呼び合える仲間が出来たと言ったら 笑うだろうか
もう顔も思い出せない 大好きだったあの人は
I can't even remember the face of the man
who meant so much to me.
キジャ 次の四龍の位置分かる
Ki-ja, do you know where the next dragon is?
Right... The next dragon is...
そうだな 次の四龍...
キジャ
Ki-ja?
Maybe it's exhaustion.
疲労...かな
ずっと全力で穴掘りしてたもんね
He was digging for a while.
キジャ
Ki-ja...
安らかに眠れ
Rest in peace.
生きとるわ
I'm alive!
There, there.
I-I'm sorry. My body feels so heavy.
申し訳ありません
体が重くて どうも 四龍の場所がいつにも増して薄ぼんやり...
The locations of the other dragons
are fainter than ever.
無理しないで
Don't push yourself too hard.
四龍の場所が分かる人ならもう一人居るけど
We have another guy who can sense
where the dragons are.
居たのか
He's here?
He's been here for a while.
実は居たんだよ 先から
青龍 他の四龍の位置分かる
Blue Dragon, do you know
where the other dragons are?
He doesn't even seem to know
what the "dragons" are.
まず四龍がなんなのか分かっていないようだ
How unfortunate.
嘆かわしい
分かっている そなたのせいではないのだ
I understand. It's not your fault.
今まで誰も教えていなかったのだから
No one has told you about them before.
From now on, I will teach you
about the four dragons.
これから私がそなたに四龍の心得を教えよう
私のことは兄と呼ぶがよい
You may call me "Brother."
He's running away?!
逃走
Maybe he didn't want to call you "Brother."
兄が不快だったんじゃね
Blue Dragon!
青龍
Blue Dragon?
Is he drowning himself?!
Drowning himself?!
身投げ
どうすんだ白蛇
What are you going to do, White Snake?
彼奴身投げしたぞ
He's trying to drown himself.
Panic
It's my fault? Is it my fault?
私のせい 私のせいなのか
Panic
B-Blue Dragon?
せ 青龍
まさか それは
Is this...
You want me to eat this
and regain my strength?
これを食べて精力をつけようと
有難いが口で言ってくれぬか
I appreciate it, but could you use words?
What will you do, Brother White Snake?
どうすんだ白蛇兄さん寒がってんぞ
He's cold.
私のせいなのか
It's my fault?
Are you okay?
大丈夫
I'm surprised you knew there was a river here.
よくここに川があるって分かったね
Oh... Those eyes can see across great distances.
その眼 遠視能力があるんだ
You caught that fish in an instant.
魚を瞬時に捕えたし 動体視力も優れてそうだね
Your kinetic vision must be excellent too.
Is it true that looking at your eyes will turn a person to stone?
その眼を見たら石になるって本当
そうなの じゃなんで面を取らないの
Really? Then why don't you take off your mask?
ね その前に火を焚いて体あっためて
First, let's make a fire, warm ourselves,
青龍のとった魚でご飯しましょう
and eat the fish the Blue Dragon caught for us.
味噌鍋か旨そうだな
Miso hotpot, huh? Looks good.
Where did you get the ingredients?
材料どこで手に入れた
青龍の里で薬と交換してもらった
I traded them for medicine
in the Blue Dragon's village.
ついでに鍋も
I got this pot too.
何時の間に
When?
ユン大変
Yun, there's a problem!
There's a bug inside the pot.
虫が鍋の中に
虫
A bug?
Scoop it out.
掬って差し上げなさい
青龍の服 乾かないわね
The Blue Dragon's clothes still aren't dry.
Yeah.
それにしても
Still...
あれはなんの妖怪だ
What kind of monster is that?
益々色物になっていくよ この集団
This group just keeps getting weirder.
Don't say that!
言うな 青龍は私のせいでああなっておるのだ
What happened to the Blue Dragon is my fault.
It must be very humiliating!
きっととても屈辱なのだ
The Blue Dragon isn't thinking anything
Blue Dragon, you'd better hurry up.
青龍 早くしないとアオが超食っちゃってるよ
Ao's eating everything.
味はどう
How does it taste?
So Good
美味しい でしょう
It's good, isn't it?
よかったね ユン
Isn't that great, Yun?
はい はい
Yeah, yeah.
Are you cold? Want to borrow my coat?
寒くない 私の外套いる
あ ありがとう ヨナ
Th-Thank you, Yona.
ヨナ
"Yona"?!
H-He used her first name.
ひ...姫様を呼び捨てに
あっさりと まぁ
Without hesitation, either.
名を呼ばれたなんて久々
It's been so long since someone
called me by my name.
私も青龍の名で呼びたい
I'd like to call you by your name too.
名はないのでしょう
You don't have a name, right?
呼んで欲しい名はある
What do you want to be called?
丸くなっちゃった
He rolled into a ball.
妖怪 毛玉でいいんじゃない
How about "Furball Monster"?
ね ユン
Hey, Yun.
青龍は好きに呼んでって言うのよ
The Blue Dragon says we can
call him whatever we want.
何で呼ぼう
What should we call him?
If I were to express the Blue Dragon in a word, it would be "silence."
俺が青龍を言葉で表すなら
静寂かな
静寂
Silence...
お姫様がしっくりくるのをつけてあげたら
Why don't you call him
whatever sounds right to you?
あの檻のような穴倉から青龍を連れだしたのはお姫様なんだから
You're the one who brought him
out of that prison-like cave.
あの面を外さないのは何か精神的なものだろうけど
There's probably some psychological reason he doesn't take off that mask,
それでもお姫様には心を開いてるっぽいし
but he seems to have opened up to you.
っていうか お姫様って本当にお姫様
Anyway, are you sure you're really a princess?
青龍に剣向けられても ひるまないし
When the Blue Dragon drew his sword on you, you didn't flinch.
穴倉に閉じ込められても挫けないしさ
Even when we were trapped inside the cave,
you didn't lose heart.
I was scared, but I'm not afraid
of the Blue Dragon.
私だって怖かったわ 青龍は怖くないけど
なに 怖いの舐めんな
What? You shouldn't underestimate fear!
It's true. Just remembering it makes me tremble.
本当よ 私 思い出しただけで震えるし
When I think about it, I can hardly breathe.
俺なんか 思い出しただけで息苦しいもんね
深呼吸して
Take deep breaths.
Yeah.
I thought royalty were dishonest and unfair,
but I'll admit I was wrong.
俺 王族って狡くて汚い奴等って思ってたけど 訂正するよ
But I hate kings and nobles and the like.
だって嫌いなんだもん 王とか貴族とか
初めて会った時 きついこと言って ごめん
I'm sorry for being so harsh
when we first met.
もしかしてずっと気にしてた
Has that been bothering you this whole time?
ユンって可愛い
You're so cute.
ちょっと水飲みに行ったくる
I'm going to get a drink.
そ それと
A-Also...
俺も名前で呼んでいい
Can I call you by your name too?
ヨナって
"Yona"?
お姫様って文字数多くて 言うのめんどくさいだよね
"Princess" is so long.
Saying it is too much trouble.
ユン 可愛い
You're so cute.
Why?
なんでだよ
いつまでついてくるの ハク
How long are you going
to keep following me, Hak?
いや 何時だったか
I'm not sure, but I think I promised to stick annoyingly close to you.
うぜぇくらい側を離れませんって約束した気がしたんで
無事に戻ってこなかったらでしょう
That was only if I didn't
make it back in one piece.
大丈夫よ 気を付けるから
I'm fine. I'll be careful.
ちょっと待ってて ヨナ...
Wait, Yona-
Princess.
姫
Hak, I want you to call me "Princess."
ハクは私のこと 姫って呼んで
ユン達はいいの
I don't mind if Yun and the others don't.
姫として出会ったんじゃなし
I didn't meet them as the princess.
仲良くしてくれて嬉しい
I'm glad they're so friendly to me.
でも お前だけは 姫って呼んで
But I want you to call me "Princess."
私が父上の イル国王の娘であること 忘れないでいて
Don't forget that I'm the daughter of King Il.
この国の誰が忘れても
Even if the rest of the kingdom forgets,
お前だけは父上とその娘を忘れないでいて
I want you to remember
my father and his daughter.
あんたが閉じ込められた時
When you were trapped, I prayed to the king not to take you away.
陛下にお願いしたんですよ 連れて行くなって
あんたを連れて行くなって
I begged him not to take you away.
他には何も望まないから それだけはやめてくれって
I said I wouldn't wish for anything else,
as long as he didn't do that.
あんたがイル陛下のご息女だって
I'm painfully aware that
you're King Il's daughter.
俺は嫌って程知っていますよ
ハクは青龍に似合う言葉 なんだと思う
Hak, what word do you think
is suited to the Blue Dragon?
Huh?
"Mask."
お面
Be serious.
真面目に
"Night," then.
じゃ 夜
夜
Night?
Silence...
静寂
I think... Well...
私は...そうね
闇の中に安らかで温かく
Despite the darkness,
he was peaceful and warm,
でも太陽より静かで青い
but he's quieter and bluer than the sun.
そんな...
Something like...
the moon.
月
シンア
Sin-ha.
It means "moonlight."
月の光と言う意味を
貴方の名はシンア
Your name is "Sin-ha."
闇の中で手を引いて導いてくれた
You led me by the hand through the darkness.
青龍は私の月の光
Blue Dragon, you are my moonlight.
どうかな
What do you think?
嫌だったか
Didn't he like it?
I think it's okay.
多分 大丈夫
Ao, my name is "Sin-ha."
アオ 俺の名前 シンアだって
初めての 俺の名前
The first name I've ever had.
Sin-ha.
シンア
あの人がくれた
She gave it to me.
大事にしよう
I will treasure it.
キジャ 具合はどう
Ki-ja, how are you feeling?
Ki-ja?
キジャ
緑
Green...
Huh?
緑龍の気配がする
I sense the Green Dragon nearby.
Do you see
wakaru kai
What I'm trying so hard to convey through my work?
muriyari demo sakuhin de tsutaetokitai koto wo
It's always been this way, hasn't it?
mukashi to kawaranai daro
The same obscure lyrics and background
yomizurai kashi mo haikei mo
I've always talked ideals
sasaeru da to ga erasou ni sa
Like supporting others
nando mo nando mo itta kedo
あの グンテ将軍 長旅で喉が渇きました
I hope you don't realize too early
kotoba no karusa omoishiru no wa
お茶をいっぱい 頂けませんか
次回 暁のヨナ 第十五話
How irresponsible I was being with my words
hayasuginai you ni
新たな地へ
There's a reason why the snow is so cold
yuki ga tsumetai wake nante
Since my hands are warmer than others'
boku no te ga hito yori atsui kara
When I hold your hand
kimi no sono te wo tsunaida toki
I'll be able to bring out the warmth in you
atatakai wo hikidasu tame
Next Time
General Geun-tae, I'm thirsty
from my long journey.
May I have a cup of tea?
Next time, Akatsuki no Yona, episode 15:
Episode 15:      To a New Land
To a New Land.